Thank you.
谢谢
Mimihime.
弥美姬
What are you daydreaming for?
你在发什么呆呀？
Class is about to start.
快要上课了
We have a test today.
今天要考试
What? Today's just a normal class, right?
什么？今天只是正常上课吧？
But, we do have one.
但我们真的要考试
Get ready for the test.
准备考试
Teacher! I haven't studied at all. It's impossible.
老师，我完全没念书耶，要怎么考啦？
Even if you had, it'd be impossible.
你即使念了也没差吧？
What?
干嘛这样？
Everyone, please be quiet.
同学们，请安静
If you paid attention in class, you'll be fine.
平常认真听课就答得出来
There are ten questions.
总共有十个问题
Why does the fish have arms?
为什么鱼有手臂？
Well, to catch other fish of course.
当然是为了抓其他的鱼咯
Have you seen one before?
你曾经见过吗？
No, I just made it up!
没有，是我的想象
Okay.
是哦
It's weird.
真诡异
Strange, right?
奇怪，对吧？
Yeah, but I want to show the Director. It's funny!
对呀，但很有趣，我想给园长看
Can I have it?
可以给我吗？
-When I've finished it, okay? -Okay.
-我画完再给你，好吗？ -好
Fifteen minutes left.
剩下15分钟
Geez! Come on.
天啊，真是的
DO YOU WANT TO GO OUTSIDE OF THE OUTSIDE?
（想去外面的外面吗？）
Outside of…
外面的…
the outside?
外面？
TENGOKU-DAIMAKYO
《天国大魔境》
So, shall we go hunting for treasure?
欸，我们来去寻宝好吗？
Sure, okay.
当然好啊
This neighborhood doesn't seem too messed up.
这个社区看来还不赖
We need to find houses that haven't been broken into.
得找到还没被破坏过的房子
Let's go further in then.
那我们走进去看看吧
It's locked. That's a good sign.
上锁了，是个好现象
Wait, Maru? Where are you? Hey, Maru!
等等，小丸？你在哪里？嘿，小丸！
Sis! We can get in from over here!
姐，我们可以从这里进去
The windows are barely broken.
窗户不至于破得太严重
I guess no one's been in here yet.
我想这里应该还没人进来过
Oh, it's a total wreck.
状况好糟糕哦
I'll go and check the other rooms.
我去其他房间看看
Oh, got a toothbrush.
找到一只牙刷
Sis!
姐
I found an unopened pack of toilet paper!
我找到一卷没用过的卫生纸
Nice one. I'm dying!
太好了，找得我快死了
Oh, no!
唉呀呀
Hey, don't look!
喂，别偷看
Well, shut the door then.
那就把门关起来呀
There is no door.
根本没有门
As if, the roof is wide open.
屋顶破了一个大洞
That's why this place is a dump.
难怪这里像个垃圾场
I'm so hungry.
我好饿
Don't say it.
别说出来
I'm trying not to think about it.
我正努力不去想这件事
What is it--
这是…
Most of the people who survived ended up dying of starvation.
大部分存活下来的人最终都饿死了
Since they died in this house,
既然他们死在这栋房子里
it means there's no food here.
就表示这里没有食物
Let's go to the next house.
我们去下一间吧
Okay.
好
Sis, this house is amazing.
姐，这间房子太棒了
It's so glamorous.
好豪华啊
Yeah, the people who lived here must have been super rich.
对呀，住在这里的人一定超有钱
NAESHIRO FAMILY
（任侠苗宅）
Wow, you finally opened the canned food?
哇，你终于把罐头打开咯？
Well, we didn't exactly find anything to eat, did we?
我们实在也没有别的选择，对吧？
Maru, can you find us some plates or something?
小丸，方便去找几个盘子吗？
On it. I'm starved.
好的，我饿死了
Hey, what's this veg stuff?
喂，这是什么青菜呀？
The weeds growing all over the place around here. I think they're edible.
这附近周围长满了杂草 我觉得是可以吃的
I thought it might fill us up a bit more.
应该可以让我们比较有饱足感
-It's so bitter. -Spit it out!
-好苦啊 -快吐出来
It stunk out the whole dish.
整道菜都是这个臭味了啦
I'm sorry!
对不起啦
That was our precious canned food!
那可是我们的宝贝罐头耶
I said I'm sorry!
我道歉了不是吗？
Is that your boyfriend?
那是你男朋友吗？
You're awake?
你醒了？
I can never fall asleep.
我根本没睡着
You're always fast asleep way before me.
你每次都比我更快睡着
Really? I guess I'm a useless bodyguard then.
真的吗？我这个保镖还真没用
I'm fine protecting myself.
我能够保护我自己
You can go back if you want.
想要的话，你可以回去
One is my friend, and the other is someone I want to see.
一个是我朋友，另一个是我想见的人
If I can find them while I take you to your destination,
如果我能够在带你前往 你目的地的途中找到他们的话
that'll be two birds with one stone.
也算是一石二鸟
That's why it's important I tag along with you.
所以我有必要跟着你走
Anyway, I'm not gonna go anywhere while you're sleeping,
总之，你睡觉的时候，我哪里都不会去
so you can relax.
你放心吧
HASSOU INN
（八巢旅馆）
So, where shall we go today?
那我们今天该去哪里呢？
We don't have enough info to go on.
我们手边没有足够的情报
I'm sick of wandering around aimlessly.
我厌烦了漫无目的地四处游荡
Well then, let's start looking for others.
那么，我们开始找其他人吧
Let's go somewhere that might be busy.
我们去一些热闹的地方
A place where people gather,
人潮应该会出现在
like somewhere with land, or near a station.
广场或是靠近车站的地方吧
Yeah, somewhere like that.
对呀，应该是吧
For now, let's walk alongside this railway track.
我们先沿着这条铁轨找吧
Great! And I want a new pair of shoes.
就这么办，我还想要一双新鞋子
Okay, okay. Let's keep an eye out for a store.
好啦，那就张大眼睛找商店咯
And after that, I'm desperate for some tasty food!
然后，我超想吃一顿好吃的
Are you still annoyed at me for yesterday, or what?
你还在为昨天的事耿耿于怀吗？
That's not what I meant!
我没有那个意思啦
Guys like you
你这种男生
are always saying stupid stuff like that, even if it is by mistake.
就是会一天到晚说出这种蠢话 尽管你是无心的
Women!
女人耶
Just when I thought life wasn't worth living.
太好了，我正想说活着一点意义都没有
Two women appear.
有两个女的耶
I'm a man.
我是男的
Great, a little brat boy.
好哦，一个小屁孩
I'm a boy too.
我也是个男孩
I'm not stupid!
你当我傻了吗？
All right, put down your heavy bags.
好的，把行李放下吧
I'm gonna take you to heaven.
我来送你们上天国
Just when I thought we'd found someone
我正想着好不容易找到人了 竟然遇上一群无赖
Whoa, wait. We don't have many bullets. Don't waste them.
等等，我们的子弹有限，别浪费
Get outta here if you want to live!
想活命的话，就给我滚
So our lives are worth less than bullets.
我们的性命连子弹都不如
They're from the lawless generation, whose world ended before it had even begun.
他们属于一个无法无天的世代 一个还没开始就结束了的世界
Who knows what they're capable of. Let's go.
谁晓得他们会做出什么傻事？我们走吧
Not like you could hit us anyway, fools!
反正你们也打不中我们，笨蛋
Damn.
可恶
Wait a sec. Is that even a real gun?
等等，那是真的枪吗？
What's this, what's this? Dropping it now, are we?
可不是嘛？把枪放下了，是吗？
I've never seen a gun that weird before.
我从来没见过这么奇怪的枪
You're just bluffing with some kid's plaything.
你只是用小孩的玩具枪在唬人
Run!
快跑
There's no escape! I won't let you make us look like idiots!
休想逃跑，少拿我们当白痴耍
It shoots…
有东西射出来了…
So, you were saying something about taking me to heaven?
你们刚说了什么？要带我去天国吗？
That was, I--
那个嘛…
We're looking for it. Heaven.
天国就是我们正在找的地方
Take us there.
带我们过去
MORIYAMA HOSPITAL
（森山医院）
Wow, what a flashy home you guys have.
哇，你们住的地方还挺浮夸的嘛
What do you think, Maru? Anything catch your attention?
你觉得呢，小丸？你看到了什么吗？
No, nothing.
没有，什么都没有
Right?
对吧？
There's no way this is the goal. It'd be a miracle.
绝不可能是这里，又不是奇迹出现
Can you charge my battery?
可以帮我的电池充电吗？
Why would I do that?
我为什么要帮你？
I don't think you're really grasping the full reality of your situation.
我想你还没搞清楚现在是什么状况
You attacked us, but we turned the tables on you.
你攻击了我们，但被我们将了一军
Even if I decide to kill you, you don't have the right to complain.
就算我决定要杀了你 你也没有抱怨的余地
We'll leave once the battery is full.
电池充饱之后我们就会离开
Please.
麻烦你了
And while we're at it, you guys heard of a place called "Heaven"?
我就加减问一下好了 你们听过一个叫「天国」的地方吗？
At this point, anywhere with "heaven" in its name,
事到如今，任何包含「天国」二字的地方
or even a place you think feels "just like heaven" will do.
甚至是任何 你们「觉得像天国」的地方都可以
As if anything like heaven exists since the Collapse.
你一副大崩坏之后 一个像天国的地方仍会存在着一样
I understand that.
我也明白
That's why I tried to make the question simpler for you.
所以我才放宽了我的标准
Do you guys like tomatoes?
你们喜欢西红柿吗？
Why? Gonna give us some?
怎样？你要给我们西红柿吗？
If you do, then I've heard of something you might call "heaven."
如果你喜欢的话 我倒是听过一个可能是「天国」的地方
-Maru, don't you like tomatoes? -Love them.
-小丸，你喜欢西红柿吗？ -喜欢
Tell us the details.
告诉我们细节吧
Here.
拿去吧
What kind of battery is that exactly?
那到底是什么东西的电池？
My gun battery.
手枪电池
You little brat!
你这个屁孩
You've been controlling us with a gun that doesn't work this whole time.
这段时间你竟然 拿了一把没用的枪牵制住我们
I wasn't even sure that last shot was gonna fire. I was out of bullets.
我甚至不确定刚刚一枪是否会成功 我的子弹都用光了
Morons! I hope you die by the roadside. Lawless youths!
混账，无法无天的年轻人 祝你们死在路边
You should respect your elders!
你们该敬老尊贤
It was no big deal. Just a bunch of old idiots.
没什么大不了，只是一群愚蠢的大叔
We got this charged up too!
手枪电池也充饱了
I feel so much better now we've got four shots.
知道能够发射四枪之后，我觉得好多了
It's probably better not to count it as four shots.
最好别当成有四枪吧
The number of times that thing doesn't work…
那个东西故障的次数…
Well anyway, off to "Tomato Heaven."
总而言之，去「西红柿天国」吧
What the hell is "Tomato Heaven"?
「西红柿天国」是什么啊？
I'm not really sure that's the best way to hold an exam.
我实在不太确定这是最佳的考试方式
Mimihime, how did you know there was going to be a test?
弥美姬，你怎么知道会有考试？
I don't know. I just had a hunch somehow.
我也不知道，就突然有个预感
But there is one thing that is certain.
但有件事我很确定
Just because you know there's a test, there's no promise of full marks.
就算知道会有考试，也不保证就能拿满分
Class is done! Let's play some sport.
今天的课都结束了，我们去运动吧
I want to continue working on this, so…
我想继续处理这个…
Then, Anzu?
杏，你呢？
No thanks.
不了，谢谢
There's no way I can win against you.
反正我一定赢不了你
Tokio?
时男呢？
Tokio has something to discuss with me. Right?
时男有话跟我说，对吧？
Fine then. I guess I'll get Kona to play with me.
好吧，那我只好找小奈陪我玩了
Where on earth does he get reflexes like that?
他的运动神经怎么会这么发达？
Kona!
小奈
You said something about the outside during the test, didn't you?
刚刚在考试的时候 你提到了有关外面的事，对吧？
What do you think the outside is like, Tokio?
时男，你认为外面是个怎么样的地方？
Outside?
外面？
Why would you ask--
你问这个干嘛？
Not here. Outside this wall.
不是这里，在这面墙之外
Isn't it just nothing?
不是什么都没有吗？
I think there is something else.
我觉得存在着某种东西
I've always had a feeling that there is.
我一直都有这种感觉
And recently, I've been able to imagine it more clearly.
最近，我想象出来的画面越来越清晰了
When I think about wanting to go outside,
当我觉得好想好想去外面的时候
two people from the outside come to help me, and one of their faces…
就会有两个人从外面进来帮我 其中一个人的脸…
DO YOU WANT TO GO OUTSIDE OF THE OUTSIDE?
（想去外面的外面吗？）
…is exactly the same as yours.
就跟你一模一样
Outside the room…
房间的外面…
outside the school…
学校的外面…
outside of…
外面的…
the outside.
外面
Tokio?
时男？
Director.
园长
If you can't sleep, do you want some medicine?
睡不着的话，要吃点药吗？
No, I…
不用了，是说…
Is there an outside beyond this one?
这里之外…还有个外面吗？
Did you think of that yourself?
这是你自己想出来的吗？
Mimihime did.
是弥美姬
That girl has a sharp intuition.
那女孩的直觉很强
Director.
园长
It's only a matter of time before they find out. Don't worry.
他们迟早会发现的，不要紧
Tokio?
时男
There is an outside beyond here.
这里之外，的确有个外面
Hey, Maru,
小丸
it may surprise you to hear this, coming from your bodyguard--
你从保镖的嘴里听到这句话 可能会吓一跳…
I'm pretty sure nothing you say could surprise me anymore.
我相当肯定，不管你说什么 都再也吓不倒我了
I can't walk any further.
我再也走不动了
What?
什么？
What? We've been sleeping outdoors, traversing mountains.
怎样啦？我们一直在跋山涉水、餐风露宿
I've reached my limit.
我已经不行了
There's nothing to eat, nowhere to sleep. I can't go on.
没东西吃、没地方睡 我没办法再继续下去了
All that talk of there being shops on every corner before the Collapse…
说什么在大崩坏以前 每个转角就会有一间商店…
Was it all a lie?
全都是一派胡言
It's just because we are on a path between cities.
城市和城市之间就是这个样子啊
You're a city girl, aren't you?
你是在都市长大的，对吧？
Exactly. I'm a Tokyo girl through and through.
没错，我就是个正宗的东京女孩
Ouch.
好痛
Let's at least find a decent spot to sleep.
我们至少得找一个像样的地方睡觉吧
Where do you get so much energy from? Is it because you're young?
你的精力怎么会这么旺盛？ 是因为你年纪小吗？
We're basically the same age.
我们基本上一样大
You're 15, right?
你15岁，对吧？
I think so. You?
我想是吧，你呢？
I'm 18, wait, 20.
我18岁，等等，20了
What's with the two-year gap?
怎么会差了两岁？
I'm not good with numbers, okay?
我的数字概念不太好
No way.
不是吧
That place is open?
那里有营业？
We are, yes.
是的，没错
Nine, ten, eleven, twelve.
9、10、11、12
All right, that'll do.
好的，这样就够了
Are you sure it's enough? It's so cheap.
你确定吗？太便宜了吧
I feel bad. Take these too.
我有点过意不去，这些也给你吧
Wow, AA batteries! Thank you!
天啊，三号电池！谢谢
Can I look at the guest book?
我可以看一下住客登记簿吗？
Go for it.
没问题
You can't get batteries like this anymore!
在这种地方
And in a place like this!
再也找不到这种电池了
He's not in here.
他不在这上面
Have you ever seen these two here?
你曾在这里见过这两个人吗？
He's good-looking. If I had, I'd remember.
是个帅哥，如果见过的话，我一定会记得
What are their names?
他们叫什么名字？
Robin Inazaki.
稻崎露敏
Well, I really don't know.
还真没听过
What about the older, punky-looking one?
那个庞克头大叔呢？
I don't know his name.
我不知道他的名字
Everyone called him "Doc" or "Sir."
大家都称呼他「医生」或「老师」
I see.
是哦
Well, that's how everyone describes this place.
这个嘛，每个来到这里的人都会这么说
It's heaven!
这里是天国啊
Kiruko.
贵留子
Y-yes.
什么事？
The mirror.
镜子啦
That's a huge crack in the mirror! I was just looking at it.
镜子上有个超大的裂痕，我忍不住一直看
The shower doesn't work, but you can use the hot bath water.
莲蓬头坏了，你可以用浴缸里的热水
There are plenty of bottles, but just use what you need.
那里有很多瓶瓶罐罐 有需要的话，就拿去用吧
The one that foams nicely is the shampoo.
很容易起泡的那罐是洗发精
We don't have power reserves here, you need to use that while the sun is up.
我们这里无法储存电力 趁太阳下山前要用赶快用
Got it.
知道了
Excuse me,
不好意思
that case, is it a gun case?
那个套子…是枪套吗？
Uh-huh. There's a monster that prowls around this area.
是的，有个怪物会在这附近出没
Don't go out wandering at night.
晚上别出去乱晃
-Monster… -Hiruko.
-怪物… -蛭子
You mean a "Man-eater"?
你说的是「食人者」对吗？
People call it different things,
它有各种各样的称号
but it's this big, confusing shape,
但它体积庞大、奇形怪状
and it eats people.
而且会吃人
We can kill it.
我们有办法杀了它
That's-- Guns have no effect on it.
是说…手枪对它起不了作用
We'll do it.
交给我们吧
My Kiru-Beam works on it, and this kid--
我的贵留光线治得住它，而这孩子…
Kiru-Beams?
贵留光线？
What?
怎样啦？
Kiru-Beam…
贵留光线…
Just because it's your beam, you named it after yourself?
因为那是你射出的光线 所以你用自己的名字来命名？
Why do you need the details?
问这么细干嘛？
You already think it's weird anyway.
反正你一直觉得很奇怪
Exactly, it's weird. That's why I'm asking.
没错，很奇怪，所以我才会问
I've made a stew with some kind of boar meat and vegetables, if you like?
我用蔬菜和某种野猪肉炖了一锅 你们想吃点吗？
Really, we can have some?
真的吗？我们可以吃吗？
It's really good!
太好吃了
I wanted to discuss something with you both.
我想跟两位讨论一件事
Well, it's a bit tricky to find the words.
实在有点难以启齿
Even though you two were raised in these strange times,
你们虽然成长于这个奇怪的时代
you use chopsticks perfectly, and seem to have been educated well.
但你们懂得正确使用筷子 而且似乎很有教养
I may be meddling, but I have to say something.
我或许是多管闲事了 但有些话我不吐不快
It's not my opinion, or a rule or anything,
这不是我的个人意见或什么教条之类的
but having children with a close relative,
但和近亲生下孩子…
genetically speaking, is fundamentally dangerous!
就基因方面来说，存在着根本的危险
What are you trying to say?
你说什么？
He might keep calling me "Sis,"
他或许姐姐长、姐姐短的
but we are not even slightly related!
但我们之间毫无血缘关系
And more to the point, we are not even dating!
更重要的是，我们甚至没在约会
I got completely the wrong idea!
我完全搞错了
Give me a break!
饶了我吧
I do all kinds of stuff in Tokyo,
我在东京什么五花八门的工作都做过
I'm sorta like an odd-job girl.
我算是那种打零工的吧
I received a request to be this guy's bodyguard during his travels.
有人请我在他旅行期间担任他的保镖
He is nothing to me beyond an object of my protection.
他对我来说只是我保护的对象而已
What's wrong, Maru? Why are you suddenly so down?
怎么了吗，小丸？ 怎么突然变得这么消沉？
Why are you dragging your futon so far away?
干嘛把床垫拉得这么远啦？
Hey, are you mad about something?
喂，你在生气吗？
Geez.
天啊
So today you fall asleep straightaway…
今天你倒是倒头就睡了
May as well go to sleep too then.
那我也上床睡觉吧
Wow.
是说…
Am I really that tired?
我真的这么累哦？
Something…
有种…
feels strange…
怪怪的感觉
Is there an outside beyond this one?
这里之外…还有个外面吗？
There is an outside beyond here.
这里之外，的确有个外面
However, it is a filthy world, a hell…
然而，那是一个肮脏的世界 潜伏着令人作恶的怪物
where abhorrent monsters lurk.
是个地狱
HEAVEN AND HELL
（天国与地狱）